Guide to the Robertson family papers, 1820-1907.
Robertson family papers, 1820-1907.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Robertson family papers, 1820-1907.
243
Robertson family
.5 cubic ft.; 2 reels microfilm; 1 painting.
Letters, school records, painting.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence and other papers of the Robertson family of Washington County, New York, and several other related families. The papers of Smith Robertson consist of his letters written while a student at Union College (Schenectady, New York) and as superintendent of Common Schools in Tompkins County; also as a medical student at Geneva Medical College, at Yale University, and while traveling to Washington, D.C.; a painting by F. E. Robertson (brother of Mary "Grandma" Moses). Robertson family genealogy; also material on related families, including Bishop, Brown, Houtz, King, Snyder, Teeter, and Wood.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence and other papers of the Robertson family of Washington County, New York, and several other related families, dealing mostly with family matters and the migration westward of family members to Ohio, Missouri, Minnesota, and California. The papers of Smith Robertson consist of his letters written while a student at Union College (Schenectady, New York) and as superintendent of Common Schools in Tompkins County; also as a medical student at Geneva Medical College, at Yale University, and while traveling to Washington, D.C. Chief subjects include education, medicine, travel, and personal affairs. Correspondents include Horace Mann, Henry Barnard, and Douglass Boardman; he also describes meeting John Quincy Adams. Also, a painting by F. E. Robertson (brother of Mary "Grandma" Moses). Robertson family genealogy, including data on George Robertson (born in Scotland and lived in Dryden, New York); Smith Robertson, Hiram Robertson (husband of Mary Cornell); also material on related families, including Bishop, Brown, Houtz, King, Snyder, Teeter, and Wood.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Robertson family.; Adams, John Quincy, 1767-1848.; Barnard, Henry.; Bishop family.; Boardman, Douglass, 1822-1891.; Brown family.; Cornell, Mary.; Houtz family.; King family.; Mann, Horace, 1796-1859.; Moses, 1860-1961.; Robertson, F. E.; Robertson, Hiram.; Robertson, Smith.; Snyder family.; Teeter family.; Wood family.; Geneva Medical College (Geneva, N.Y.)--Students.; Union College (Schenectady, N.Y.)--Students.
Subjects:
Medical education--New York (State)--Geneva.; Teachers colleges--New York (State); Education--New York (State)--Ithaca.; Schools--Administration--New York (State)--Tompkins County.; Medicine--Study and teaching--New York (State)--Geneva.; Migration, Internal--Ohio.; Migration, Internal--Missouri.; Migration, Internal--Minnesota.; Migration, Internal--California.; Family--New York (State)--Washington County.
Places:
Washington County (N.Y.)--Genealogy.; Washington, D.C.--Description and travel.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Includes collections #184, #243, #908, and #852.
CONTAINER LIST
- September 1840 - December 1841 10 items (Folder 1)
  - September 5, 1840 (Folder 1)
    From Smith Robertson at Union College, Schenectady, to his parents, Mr. and Mrs. George Robertson, at Varna; is concerned with the College. (SR member of July 1843 graduating class.)
  - November 15, 1840 (Folder 1)
    To SR, Union, from E. Canfield, Sandisfield.
  - November 29, 1840 (Folder 1)
    From W. Smith at Yale to SR at Union; is concerned with life at Yale; courses; death of a friend.
  - November (?) (Folder 1)
    From SR at Union to William H. Lacy at Cortland Academy, Homer. "Seward runs behind while Bouck runs far ahead of his ticket"; other political comments. Also, references to college life, studies, professors.
  - March 15, 1841 (Folder 1)
    From B. C. Whiting, Binghamton, to SR.
  - March 25, 1841 (Folder 1)
    From O. S. Wood, Dryden, to SR at Union.
  - April [6] 1841 (postmark) (Folder 1)
    Printed report form from Union; addressed to George Robertson; includes tuition bill and marks for term January 8-April 1, 1841; also general information on courses, admission requirements, etc.
  - May 21, 1841 (Folder 1)
    From Ruel Smith, Rochester, who is studying medicine in the office of a professor of surgery at Geneva Medical College; mentions practices of medical students who procured corpses already buried for their dissections. To SR at Union.
  - August 11, 1841 (Folder 1)
    Term report from Union as in April above; for period April 30-July 28, 1841.
  - December 9, 1841 (Folder 1)
    From Cousin Molly, Albany, to SR at Union.
- January 1842 - October 1842 11 items (Folder 2)
  - January 8 (Folder 2)
    From SR at Union College to William H. Lacy, Cortlandville; remarks about newly elected state legislators; plans for present term at College and future entering of Law School.
  - February 21, 1842 (Folder 2)
    To SR at Union from N. B. Smith, Ithaca.
  - April 9 (postmark) (Folder 2)
    Term report from Union for period January 7-April 1, 1842.
  - May 12 or 13 (sic), 1842 (Folder 2)
    From William Smith at Yale to SR at Union.
  - May 29, 1842 (Folder 2)
    From Howard Townsend, Albany, to SR at Union; tells of H's journey to Washington, D.C.; his meeting John Quincy Adams, Daniel Webster, hearing Henry Clay speak, dining at the White House with President Tyler, and seeing the sights of the Capital.
  - July 8, 1842 (Folder 2)
    From James Wood, Jr., Union College, to SR in Dryclen, about an overpayment of a debt; SR now in a lawyer's office.
  - July 12, 1842(postmark) From Isaac Mott to SR at Union. (Folder 2)
  - July 25, 1842 (Folder 2)
    To SR from a cousin. Tells of the illness of his Aunt Sally.
  - August 10, 1842 (postmark) (Folder 2)
    Term report from Union for period April 29th-July 27, 1842
  - September 5, 1842 (Folder 2)
    From Cyrus Robertson in Albion, Michigan, to his brother, SR; concern about worth of Michigan land SR wishers to sell
  - October 12, 1842 (Folder 2)
    From Walter Mott, cousin of SR; invitation to SR to visit Mott in Albany at; the Medical College and perhaps see an operation performed.
- January 29, 1843 - October 7, 1843 9 items (Folder 3)
  - January 29, 1843 (Folder 3)
    From Howard Townsend at Union to SR in Etna.
  - February (?), 1843 (Folder 3)
    From Mitchell (fraternity brother of SR?); "Ike" and others to SR.
  - March 31, 1843 (Folder 3)
    From N. R. Biddlecomb, and others to SR urging his return to Union Coll. and reporting events since his departure.
  - April 10, 1843 (Folder 3)
    From State of New York, Secretary's Office, Department of Common Schools Albany to SR--Superintenderit of Common Schools, Tompkins Co., Ithaca. Re: a law of 1843 stating that all appeals presented to the State Secretary's Office must have first been submitted to and had a decision rendered by th& superintendent of schools in the particular county.
  - April 16, 1843 (Folder 3)
    From M. Scofield, Whitesboro, to SR.
  - May 1, 1843 (Folder 3)
    From SR at. Union Coll. to parents; has returned to College
  - May 23, 1843 (Folder 3)
    From D. R. Houts, Ithaca, to SR at Union College.
  - May 23, 1843 (Folder 3)
    From Hiram D. Robertson at Albion, Michigan, to Parents (George Robertson) about trip to Detroit.
  - October 7, 1843 (Folder 3)
    From Asa Barton, Union Coll. to SR at Varna, Tompkins Co. about news of SR's fraternity at Union, Sigma Phi.
- January 9, 1844 - April 16, 1844 11 items (Folder 4)
  - January 9 (Folder 4)
    From W. Smith at Yale University to SR, Varna, Tompkins Co., N.Y,. ,some facts about life at Yale and news of friends
  - January 18, 1844 (Folder 4)
    From S. Town of Aurora to SR; letter is about Town helpinc Robertson with a "pioneer enterprise thro' which the cause of primary education will receive so much aid."
  - February 15, 1844 (Folder 4)
    From H. Gillam of Aurora to SR about the possible visit of a Mr. Town.
  - February 27, 1844 (Folder 4)
    From S. Town of Aurora to SR; letter says that a visit to Tompkins Co. would be impossible. Town speaks of a project undertaken by Tompkins Co. teachers that has spread to other parts of the State; he commends the venture and wishes them success in the future.
  - March 6, 1844 (Folder 4)
    From A. Potter, Union College, to SR, Ithaca. Potter isn't sure whether or not he will be able to attend an Institute.
  - March 11, 1844 (Folder 4)
    From S. Young, Secretary's Office, Department of Common Schools, Albany to SR, Superintendent of Tompkins Co. Common Schools re: teacher certification for a Mr. Curtis and commending SR on the reputation of the Teachers' Institute
  - March 11, 1844 (Folder 4)
    From D. A. Morton, town clerk, Groton, to SR, Super. Common Schools of Tompkins County, listing names of district clerks for the Groton Common Schools.
  - March 20, 1844 (Folder 4)
    From Eleaser Carter of Caroline, to SR informing SR that the trustees have refused his (SR's) request for a meeting. Carter says that he will arrange for SR to review the clerk's books and will give SR all the help that he can.
  - March 21, 1844 (Folder 4)
    From Cyrus Clark and John S. Holden to SR as Superintendent of Tompkins Co. Common Schools. A notice of an appeal being sent to the N.Y.S. Superintendent of Schools concerning the Board of Trustees' refusal to comply with anexisting statute. SR. had ruled in favor of the Trustees.
  - March 27, 1844 (Folder 4)
    George B. Glendening, Cayuga Academy, Aurora to SR; acceptance of invitation to visit SR.
  - March 30, 1844 (Folder 4)
    From S. Young, State of New York Secretary's Office, Dept of Common. Schools, to SR. State Superintendent upholds decision of SR in the case of Holden and Clark vs. the Trustees of the town, of Lansing District #7, saying that trustees have right to levy tax.
  - April 3, 1844 (Folder 4)
    From Douglass Boardman, Trumansburg, to SR. Letter tells of the electioneering done by Boardman's opponents in an election in the attempts to get another man elected.
  - April 16, 1844 (Folder 4)
    From S. Town, Angelica, to SR; reports on the Teacher's Institute in Angelica.
- May 27, 1844 - December 31, 1844 14 items (Folder 5)
  - May 27, 1844 (Folder 5)
    To SR from. S.D. Carr of Groton. A man in the school district refuses to pay taxes on land which is not in said district.
  - June 4, 1844 (Folder 5)
    From Douglass Boardman, Trumansburg, to SR requesting that SR send the dates he will be able to visit Trumansburg.
  - June 29, 1844 (Folder 5)
    Printed invitation from Alpha of the Sigma Phi with note from How(ard?) Porter.
  - July 29, 1844 (Folder 5)
    To SR from S. D. Carr asking that SR visit the Groton district schools and commenting on the next school term.
  - August 12, 1844 (Folder 5)
    From Lyman Cobb, N.Y.C. to SR about text books being considered by the Books Committee of the County School Association.
  - August 13, 1844 (Folder 5)
    From S. Young, Secretary's Office, Dept. of Common Schools, Albany, to SR granting the request for an extension in handing in the district's annual report and commending the evaluation SR is doing of the Common Schools in Tompkins Co.
  - August 13, 1844 (Folder 5)
    From Douglass Boardman, Trumansburg, to SR. The State Superintendent has asked that each district send in the number and description of the books in the school libraries. Boardman also reports that a district meeting will soon take place to discuss new school sites and taxes.
  - September 4, 1844 (Folder 5)
    From S. Young, Secretary's Office, Department of Common Schools, Albany to SR. The state regulation calling for a catalogue of books held by each district must be followed.
  - September 21, 1844 (Folder 5)
    To SR from D. W. Carley, Newfield. Carley tells of his plans for the ending of the school term and the examination of his pupils.
  - October 3, 1844 (Folder 5)
    From S. Town to SR. Town "will come to Ithaca."
  - October 17, 1844 (Folder 5)
    From E. Powell, Owego, to SR. Letter sends news of Teacher Institute.
  - October 21, 1844 (Folder 5)
    From S. D. Carr, Groton, to SR. Letter about the possible hiring of a Mr. Everson in SR's district.
  - December 3, 1844 (Folder 5)
    From Alex Holland, Union Coll., to SR. Acknowledgment payment of money to Union College.
  - Decemeber 31, 1844 (Folder 5)
    From Horace Mann, Boston, to SR. Can not meet with SR until following April. Commends SR for his (SR's) new work in New York State common schools.
- January 10, 1845 - July 18, 1845 15 items (Folder 6)
  - January 10, 1845 (Folder 6)
    From P. A. Ely, Hector, to SR, Superintendent Tompkins Co. Common Schools. A request of SR can not be fulfilled and Ely does not, have a candidate for the Norman (?) School.
  - January 15, 1845 (Folder 6)
    From Robert Alien, Joseph Ammack, Samuel Alien, Jonathan Owen, Woodard White, and John Fish, all of Enfield, to SR, Superintendent of Tompkins Co. Common Schools. Letter is an appeal to SR in behalf of a poor family in the school district. The District Board of Trustees has demanded the payment of the rate bill by this man who does not have the money. The petitioners are asking SR to exempt this man from the rate bill.
  - March 8, 1845 (Folder 6)
    From S. Town of Aurora to SR, Supt. Tompkins Co. Common School. S. Town can not accept invitation of SR.
  - March 10, 1845 (Folder 6)
    From E. G. Starke, Auburn, to SR. A letter which SR mailed to Starke had been sent to the wrong address and the event which Starke had been invited to, had already taken place. Starke is angered by a movement in Albany seeking to abolish County Superintendents. He attacks Silas Wright, U.S. Senator 1833; reelected 1837 and 1843; governor 1845-47, as being the American Cato and states that Wright has not the information needed to make the statements he has been making. Starke comes out against "bigotry and ignorance coupled with rank injustice in high stations."
  - March 15, 1845 (Folder 6)
    From Edwin Cooper, Waterloo Academy, to SR. Cooper can not "during his vacation" visit SR but will be in Ithaca for two days during the next institute. He praises SR's work and comments on the effect it has upon other counties.
  - March 25, 1845 (Folder 6)
    From S. Young, Ballston, to SR, Ithaca. The letter is an answer to an invitation of SR to Young. Young talks about the prejudices of certain segments of the community against the school system. Young says that education is not for the rich alone, as the mass of people think, but for the poor as well. No one should be denied the opportunity of receiving an education. '"No philanthropist should remit his exertions until our Schools are raised to such a grade of utility as to embrace all the children of the State, the sons and daughters of the rich as well as of the poor. All should here mingle on one common level; all should be blended into one mass during the susceptible period of youth. This is the only means of promoting the harmony of society, of suppressing jealousies and perpetuating in letter and in spirit our republican institutions."
  - April 7, 1845 (Folder 6)
    From Edwin Cooper, Waterloo to SR, Ithaca. Cooper will not be able to attend the Teacher Institute in Ithaca because of the illness of his wife.
  - May 4, 1845 (Folder 6)
    From Cyrus Robertson, Albion, Michigan, to his brother Smith Robertson, Ithaca.
  - May 30, 1845 (Folder 6)
    Lovel (?) Preston, Caroline, to SR. Letter is praising SR for his system of school instruction.
  - July 1, 1845 (Folder 6)
    Printed folder - written by Franklin Knight. The folder is a sort of advertisement for a book of facsimiles of letter from George Washington on agriculture Knight has published that will "have a most salutary influence in correcting, in the youth of our country, many false notions regarding the character of agricultural pursuits."
  - July 1, 1845 (Folder 6)
    Printed circular for Wickham's "Educational Incentives," particularly Teacher's Tokens with facsimile. Letter from the publisher, Alexander V. Blake, N.Y.C. to SR, telling SR about the invention of a School Ledger which would enable a teacher to keep permanent records of students.
  - July 2, 1845 (Folder 6)
    From I (?) Cooper McLean, N.Y., to SR. A new certificate is to be made out for Miss Samantha Burton enaibling her to teach in any school district in Tompkins' County.
  - July 4, 1845 (Folder 6)
    Printed circular from R. Hyde Walworth, President, New York Juvenile Temperance Association to SR and all County and town superintendents, urging them to promote said association and its goals in their district or county.
  - July 7, 1845 (Folder 6)
    From Francis Dwight, Albany, to SR. A Mr. D. P. Page will be in the area in the middle of September and will be willing to address a Teacher Institute if there is one at that time.
  - July 18, 1845 (Folder 6)
    From Henry McGonegal of Albany, asking SR for a recommendation. McGonegal is seeking a position in Syracuse as a teacher.
- August 11, 1845 - November 13, 1845 10 items (Folder 7)
  - August 11, 1845 (Folder 7)
    From Albert D. Wright, Verona to SR, Ithaca. Dwight had promised SR that he would speak at the Tompkins County Teachers' Institute. He is asking to be released from this engagement since he is being asked by his own district (county) to be in charge of an Institute there.
  - August 11, 1845 (Folder 7)
    From E. C. Seymour, Albany, to SR, Ithaca. Letter informs that Seymour will be leaving the school at the end of the term. Professors Perkins and Page will not be able to attend the Tompkins County Institute. Seymour asks the help of SR in finding a job for the next term.
  - August 13, 1845 (Folder 7)
    Circular giving details of the coming Cayuga County Teachers' Institute.
  - September 14, 1845 (Folder 7)
    From Henry Barnard of Providence to SR, Ithaca. Barnard will be able to attend the Institute and will deliver an address on "What can be done to improve the schools this winter?"
  - October 5, 1845 (Folder 7)
    From Henry Barnard,Providence, to SR, Ithaca. The letter confirms Barnard's appearance at the Teachers' Institute, October 14 and announces his plans for an earlier arrival.
  - October 22, 1845 (Folder 7)
    From Edwin Cooper, Syracuse, to SR, Ithaca. Cooper will not be able to attend the Teachers' Institute. He also encourages SR to accept a copy of a "current volume of the Advocates'" and to encourage the teachers in his district to become subscribers.
  - October 27, 1845 (Folder 7)
    From O. O. Wickham, N.Y.C. to SR. Wickham will not be able to attend the Institute and present his "Educational Incentives" to the teachers present. However, he is sending samples and asks that a wall chart called School Chart of Characteristics be placed on the wall of some room at the Institute.
  - October 30, 1845 (Folder 7)
    From Charles R. Coburn, Owego, to SR inviting SR and Mr. Barnard to the Owego Institute and Esq. Gillet, if he can be spared. He invites SR to speak to them about education.
  - November 8, 1845 (Folder 7)
    From Daniel Jackson, Burdett, to SR about a teacher, Mr. J. W. Carpenter, then teaching at his school, who had the previous year been in trouble over a young woman of the town whom he had since married. Jackson says that except for that one incident, Carpenter's reputation and behavior had been very fine.
  - November 13, 1845 (Folder 7)
    From O. O. Wickham, N.Y.C. to SR asking for the names of all of those present at the last Teachers' Institute so that he may advertise his Teacher's Book of Instrumentalities and School Requisites.
- January 27, 1846 - July 28, 1846 12 items (Folder 8)
  - January 27, 1846 (Folder 8)
    From Thomas Slater, Albany, to SR, Professor Perkins will be able to attend the Institute planned for the spring.
  - February 17, 1846 (Folder 8)
    From H. Camp, school trustee in Trumansburg, to SR, Supt. of Common Schools, Tompkins County in regard to a notice that there will be a public examination of students in the near future. Camp says, on behalf of the other trustees, that their school will not be taking part in the examination.
  - March 19, 1846 (Folder 8)
    From C. S. Ford, Geneva to SR about Ford's appearance as a lecturer at a future Teachers' Institute.
  - March 26, 1846 (Folder 8)
    From S. Town, Aurora to SR. Town cannot, at the time, indicate whether or not he will be able to visit Ithaca.
  - April 8, 1846 (Folder 8)
    From G. H. Stevens, Danby, to SR. Sherman Miller has been newly elected Town Superintendent of Schools. Canfield and Stevens are going to School [to keep school?]
  - May 20, 1846 (Folder 8)
    From Doug(lass) (Boardman) Trumansburg, to SR as Superintendent of Common Schools, Tompkins Co. giving exact time of his arrival in Ithaca.
  - May 26, 1846 (Folder 8)
    SR from T. Russell Jencks of Boston.
  - June 15, 1846 (Folder 8)
    From Palmer and Jencks, Boston, to SR, Supt. of Common Schools. They have found the journals he enquired about and wish to know if he wants them to be sent to him.
  - July 1, 1846 (Folder 8)
    Printed circular from N. S. Benton, Supt., N.Y.S., Secretary's Office, Dept. of Common Schools. A previous circular should be disregarded if it does not apply to a particular Superintendent,.
  - July 10, 1846 (Folder 8)
    From J. S. (or I. S.) Mitchell, Canajoharie, to SR.
  - July 28, 1846 (Folder 8)
    From Superintendent of Caroline to SR reporting on the salary of the County and town superintendent of schools note attached re: amount of compensation for Dr. Farlin [See Ace. #2241]. Town Superintendent.
- August 12, 1846 - October 26, 1846 11 items (Folder 9)
  - August 12, 1846 (Folder 9)
    From Jacob Abbott of New York to SR. Abbott is not certain whether or not he will be able to attend an Institute scheduled for early October. He thanks SR for the positive information and says that he will send a definite answer when he is able to.
  - August 15, 1846 (Folder 9)
    From C. La. (?) Ford, Medina to SR of Ithaca. Ford is not certain whether or not he will be able to speak on Anatomy and Physiology at an Institute in the early part of October
  - September 11, 1846 (Folder 9)
    From A.J. Tompkins of Lansing inviting SR to their school celebration.
  - September 21, 1846 (Folder 9)
    From Alonzo Wynkoop, Chemung, to SR of Ithaca. Wynkoop asks for SR's assistance in finding qualified teachers to lead an Institute.
  - September 26, 1846 (Folder 9)
    From Horace Mann, Boston to SR. Mann sends his regrets and says he will not be able to attend their Institute. He commends SR for the work he is doing.
  - September 26, 1846 (Folder 9)
    Printed circular from Andrews and Boyle, Publishers, N.Y.C. to SR requesting the names and mailing addresses of all the town superintendents in the county and all of the teachers in the county. Andrews and Boyle are publishing a weekly newspaper, the Anglo Saxon, and hope to interest the superintendents and teachers in becoming subscribers.
  - October 5, 1846 (Folder 9)
    From Jacob Abbott, N.Y., to SR. Abbott will be able to visit the Institute.
  - October 8, 1846 (Folder 9)
    Printed circular from 0. C. Gardiner of N.Y.C. to SR, Supt. of Common Schools, Tompkins County. Circular is a testimonial for the magazine American Quarterly Journal of Agriculture and Science; hand written letter {pages 2-3) is sent to encourage SR to subscribe to magazine.
  - October 8, 1846 (Folder 9)
    From Oliver Dyer of New York to SR. Mr. Augustus Boyle will not be able to address 'the Teachers' Institute on Phonographics and sends his regrets.
  - October 16, 1846 (Folder 9)
    From P. S. Ely, Hector, to SR of Ithaca. Ely's visit to Ithaca has been postponed a week. The Burdett School is in need of a teacher and Ely suggests that SR send them one.